Guide to the Jimmy Creech Papers, 1972-2014 RL.11114
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jimmy Creech papers
1972-2014 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Creech, Jimmy, 1944-
Long, Patricia
RL.11114
16.5 Linear Feet
16 Megabytes
James (Jimmy) Edward Creech (1944-) is a former United Methodist minister and activist. Creech was an ordained elder in The United Methodist Church from 1970 to 1999, serving as a minister in North Carolina and Omaha, Nebraska, and as the North Carolina Council of Churches' liaison with the North Carolina General Assembly. An outspoken advocate for gay rights, Creech performed dozens of holy union ceremonies as a pastor in the 1990s. The United Methodist Church passed legislation prohibiting such unions in 1996. In 1999, The United Methodist Church revoked his credentials of ordination following two church trials for defying this prohibition by conducting covenant ceremonies for two same-sex couples in 1997 and 1999. Since his defrocking, Creech has continued his work as an LGBTQ rights-activist, traveling across the country to push for civil and human rights for members of the LBGTQ community. The collection includes printed material, documentation of the church trials, and Creech's writings, including the original unedited manuscript of his memoir, Adam's Gift, initially entitled, The Church on Trial.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Conditions Governing Access
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Jimmy Creech Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Arrangement
Arranged into series: Church Life, Activist Work, and Writings. Arrangement and folder titles generated by creator.
Biographical / Historical
James (Jimmy) Edward Creech, born October 21, 1944, holds a master's of divinity from Duke University, granted in 1970. Following his ordination, he served as a minister at several churches in North Carolina, including Warsaw United Methodist Church and Fairmont United Methodist Church in Raleigh. He began to advocate for gay rights after a congregant came out to him in 1984. While at Fairmont between 1987 and 1990, he co-founded and was chairperson of the Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality, an ecumenical group designed to publicly challenge religious antigay rhetoric. Due to backlash following his outspoken advocacy for gay rights, including his decision to march in a gay pride parade, Creech was denied reappointment as minister of Fairmont in 1990. From 1991 to 1996, Creech was the Program Associate with the North Carolina Council of Churches. He was the council's legislative liaison with the North Carolina General assembly, and represented the council on issues including the abolition of the death penalty, farm workers, campaign finance reform, and the repeal of the Crimes Against Nature law. In 1996, he was appointed Senior Pastor at the First United Methodist Church in Omaha, Nebraska. In September, 1997, he joined two women in a "holy union" despite orders issued in 1996 by The United Methodist Church prohibiting such unions. After the union, he was suspended from ministry and was put on trial in March, 1998, by The United Methodist Church under the charge of violating the Order and Discipline of The United Methodist Church. The trial ended in Creech's acquittal, but he was not reappointed to First United Methodist Church, Omaha, as Senior Pastor. He took a voluntary leave of absence and returned to Raleigh. While in Raleigh, in 1999 Creech joined another same-sex couple in a holy union. He was again put on trial by the church, at which he was convicted and defrocked. Since the summer of 1998 and his defrocking in 1999, Creech has continued to advocate for LGBTQ rights, especially for gays and lesbians within faith communities. He has traveled around the country preaching in churches and speaking on college campuses about human and civil rights for members of the LGBT community. He has co-founded and guided several LGBTQ rights organizations, namely SoulForce and Faith in America. His memoir, Adam's Gift: A Memoir of a Pastor's Calling to Defy the Church's Persecution of Lesbians and Gays, published in 2011, details the church trials as well as his work as an ally for the gay community. Creech is retired and lives in Raleigh.
Related Materials
Rubenstein Library also holds the United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940.
Collection Overview
Organized into three series, Church Life, Activist Work, and Writings, the Jimmy Creech papers (12,375 items) contain correspondence, notes, research files, printed material, ephemera, clippings and articles, and audio recordings from Creech's time as a United Methodist minister and LGBT rights activist. The papers span 1981-2014, with a bulk of the collection covering the 1990s during which time he was a United Methodist minister in North Carolina, the Program Associate for the North Carolina Council of Churches, and eventually became the senior pastor at First United Methodist Church in Omaha, Nebraska. A bulk of the Church Life series covers the two church trials brought against Creech in 1998 and 1999 by The United Methodist Church for his conducting covenant ceremonies for same-sex couples. Much of this series consists of correspondence received by Creech from his supporters and opponents during these trials. The Activist Work series holds files from Creech's advocacy for civil and human rights, especially for members of the LGBT community. Activist Work series documents Creech's speaking engagements and attendance at conferences across the country in support of LGBT rights. This series also contains files from Creech's work against the death penalty, including correspondence with death row inmates in the 1990s. A part of the Activist Work series, The RRNGLE (Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality) subseries contains materials created and given to Creech by RRNGLE member Patricia Long. Creech was co-founder and chairperson of RRNGLE, an ecumenical group designed to publicly challenge religious antigay rhetoric. Long's files include interviews with RRNGLE members and documents pertaining to her efforts to publish a book on the organization. Original audiovisual material and electronic records are also included in the collection.
United Methodist Church (U.S.); Church controversies -- Methodist Church; Methodist Church -- United States -- Clergy; Homosexuality -- Religious aspects -- United Methodist Church (U.S.); Capital punishment -- Religious aspects -- United Methodist Church (U.S.); Gay rights; Marriage -- Religious aspects; Machine-readable artifacts; Fairmount United Methodist Church (Raleigh, N.C.); First United Methodist Church (Omaha, Neb.); Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality
- Church Life, 1
  Scope and Contents
  The Church Life series documents Creech's work as a United Methodist minister in North Carolina and Omaha, Nebraska. The series contains papers beginning in 1981 from Creech's time at Warsaw United Methodist Church in Warsaw, NC through his defrocking in 1999. The bulk of the series comprises correspondence with parishioners and church officials, media coverage of his time as pastor including his sometimes controversial support of gay rights issues, church newsletters, and printed material. The First Trial and Second Trial subseries document the two church trials held in Nebraska that eventually led to Creech's defrocking in 1999.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  - All Church Conference FUMC, 1997
    - All Church Conference FUMC, 1997 (Box 1)
    - All Church Conference tape 2, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0025)
    - All Church Conference tape 4, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0027)
    - All Church Conference Tape #1 side A, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0001)
    - All Church Conference Tape #1 side B, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0002)
    - All Church Conference tape 3, 1997 (Box 12, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0015)
    - All Church Conference Tape #2 side A, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0003)
    - All Church Conference Tape #2 side B, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0004)
    - All Church Conference Tape #3 side A, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0005)
    - All Church Conference Tape #3 side B, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0006)
    - All Church Conference Tape #4 side A & B, 1997 (Box 11, Audio-cd RL-11114-CD-0007)
    - All Church Conference tape 1, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0029)
  - General Correspondence, Newsletters, and Administrative files
    - Board of Ministry, UMC, North Carolina, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Warsaw United Methodist Church Newsletters, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1993; 1 folder (Box 1)
    - Fairmont UMC, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Fairmont Focus (newsletter), 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - "Fairmont and Jimmy Creech", 1996 (Box 1)
    - Fairmont UMC Clippings, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - "The Controversy", 1988-1989 (Box 1)
      Folder contains documents about Creech's decision to march in a gay pride parade. The backlash from this decision eventually led to his not being reappointed as minister at Fairmont UMC.
    - Leave of Absence, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Letters of support to Creech following leave of absence, 1990-1992; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Creech Support Fund, 1990; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Non-Supportive letters to Creech, 1990 (Box 1)
    - North Carolina Council of Churches, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - North Carolina Council of Churches, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
    - Pullen Memorial Baptist Church, undated (Box 1)
    - Fairmont UMC Staff-Parish Relations Committee, undated (Box 1)
    - First United Methodist Church Omaha Appointment, 1996 (Box 1)
    - First United Methodist Church Omaha History, undated (Box 1)
    - First United Methodist Church Omaha 1997 Finances (Box 1)
    - Sermons at First United Methodist Church Omaha, 1997 (Box 1)
    - First United Methodist Church Omaha responses and correspondence following holy union ceremony, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Leave of Absence from First United Methodist Church Omaha, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Presbyterian Church USA Reports to the General Assembly, 1991 (Box 1)
    - UM Retreat Ecumenism and Homosexuality, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Electronic emails and administrative files, 1996-2003; 22 3.5 inch floppy discs contain 210 files; 12 MB (Digital-materials RL11114-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      Emails and documents in html, rfc822, MS doc, and gif formats.
      Collection contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  - First Trial, 1
    The First Trial subseries documents the trial held against Creech by The United Methodist Church in March, 1998. Creech was charged with violating the Order and Discipline of The United Methodist Church for celebrating a covenant ceremony for two women in Omaha, Nebraska in September, 1997. Subseries comprises correspondence, trial transcripts, clippings, and Creech's notes on the trial proceedings. Contains correspondence with Nebraska Bishop Joel Martinez and Creech's advisors, including his wife, Chris Weedy. Subseries contains defense team correspondence and notes. A bulk of the subseries contains positive letters of support Creech received during the trial as well as negative letters condemning his actions
    - Jury Selection Transcript (Box 2)
    - Trial Proceedings Transcript, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Committee of investigation hearing and trial transcripts (Box 2)
    - Bill Jenks, 1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Pre-trial correspondence, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Pre-trial reaction, undated (Box 2)
    - Pre-trial correspondence, 1998-2001 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence post-acquittal, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Judicial Process, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Supporting the Vision scrapbook, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook from FUMC Supporting the Vision, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook from FUMC correspondence with Bishop Martinez, undated; 1 folder (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook from FUMC, 1996-1998; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - "And God Will Raise You Up?" messages of support for Jimmy Creech from the Methodist Federation for Social Action, undated (Box 2)
    - Administrative and Judicial Procedures Handbook, undated (Box 2)
    - Complaint Response Package, undated (Box 2)
    - Defense Team Memoranda and Communiques, undated (Box 2)
    - Defense Team Notes and Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - Trial Information for First United Methodist Church Omaha Members, undated (Box 2)
    - Media Information from the Reconciling Congregation Program, undated (Box 2)
    - Reaction to Trial #1, undated (Box 2)
    - Response to the Judicial Charge by Jimmy Creech, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Supporting the Vision: First United Methodist Church, Omaha, NE, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Chris Weedy's notes and correspondence, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - First United Methodist Church Omaha- Post Trial #1 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters, undated (Box 3, Oversize-folder 1)
    - In Search of Unity, undated (Box 3)
    - Council of Bishops Lincoln, NE, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Community Rally, First United Methodist Church Omaha, April 19th, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Post FUMC- Pre-Trial #2, undated (Box 3)
    - Re: Not to Be Reappointed at First United Methodist Church Omaha, undated (Box 3)
    - Jeules material, undated (Box 3)
    - Suspension, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - PFLAG, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - CORNET (Covenant Relationships Network), undated (Box 3)
    - Kathy Russell Consultations, 1997 (Box 3)
    - MCC Support, undated (Box 3)
    - Dumbarton UMC, Holy Unions, undated (Box 3)
    - Response to Judicial Charge, undated (Box 3)
    - Social Principles of UMC, 1996 (Box 3)
    - In all Things Charity, undated (Box 3)
    - Confessing Movement, undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Open Letter to Bishops, 1998 (Box 3)
    - UM Bishops, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Reaction to trial #1, undated (Box 3)
    - Letters to Bishop Martinez in support of Creech, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Letters to Bishop Martinez, Joanie Zetterman, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Letters in support of Creech to Chris Weedy, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Letters of support to Creech from church groups, 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re: trial, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with Bob and Betty Dorr, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Letters of support to Creech, 1997-1998; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Letters of support to Creech, 1997-1998; 18 folders (Box 4)
    - Letters of support to Creech, 1998 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Letters of support to Creech, 1997-2002 and undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Non-supportive letters to Creech, 1997-1998; 6 folders (Box 5)
    - The Gateway newsletter, undated (Box 5)
    - Media Coverage, 1996-1998; 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Judicial Complaint Process, 1997-2001; 1 3.5 floppy disc containing 28 files; less than 1 MB. (Digital-materials RL11114-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      Correspondence files in Lotus Word Pro, html, rfc822, and txt formats.
  - Second Trial, 2
    The Second Trial subseries contains Creech's documentation from his second trial held by The United Methodist Church on the charge of violating the Order and Discipline of The United Methodist Church for celebrating a holy union for two men in April 1999. The Second Trial subseries contains defense strategies, correspondence from the trial, clippings and other media coverage of the 1999 trial.
    - Defense Strategies, 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Grand Island, Nebraska (Box 5)
      Creech's second trial was held in Grand Island, Nebraska.
    - Soulforce re:trials, undated (Box 5)
    - Trial Correspondence, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Trial Drama, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Defense fund, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Reaction-trial #2, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Support letters from Vigil Binkley Baptist Church, 1999 November 11 (Box 5)
    - Affirmation, undated (Box 5)
    - Response to James Creech ruling re: constitutionality of Holy Unions, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Judicial process #2, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Letters of support to Creech, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
    - Holy Union, Jim and Larry, 1999; 1 folder (Box 5)
    - Media coverage, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Articles re: Talk in Newton, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Media coverage, 2000-2001; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1990-2001 (Box 5)
    - Trial Support Letters, Drama, and Soulforce Action, 1997-2003; 5 3.5 inch floppy discs containing 281 files; 1.33 MB (Digital-materials RL11114-SET-0001, Box Digital Media Box 1)
      Emails, letters, press releases, and written statements in html, rfc822, txt, and Lotus Word Pro formats.
  - Recorded Sermons
    Subseries contains audiocasette recordings of select sermons given by Creech from 1997 to 1999.
    - The Lie of Violence, the Truth of Love, 1997 (Box 12, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0013)
    - Disorderly Conduct, Mark 3:20-35, 1997 (Box 12, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0014)
    - One life together, John 6:24-35, 1997 (Box 12, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0015)
    - The Empty Tomb, Easter Sunday, 1997 (Box 12, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0017)
    - Gifts of Grace, Mark 6:14-29, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0018)
    - Share Bread with the Hungry, Matthew 25:31-46, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0019)
    - Pentecost: Power, Unity, and Vision, John 15:26-27; 16:4b-15, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0020)
    - Be Doers of the World, Mark 7:1-8, 14-15, 21-23, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0021)
    - Vision: New Wineskin for New Wine, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0022)
    - The Spirit of Giving, Mark 10:17-31 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0023)
    - Embody the Faith, John 20:19-31, 1997 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0024)
    - Sign of the Rainbow, 1998 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0026)
    - Easter Sunday When the Future Opened, 1998 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0028)
    - Pride Sunday, 1999 (Box 13, Audio-cassette RL-11114-CS-0030)
- Activist Work, 2
  The Activist Work series contains printed material, correspondence, documents concerning travel engagements, and media coverage of Creech's efforts as an activist during his time as an ordained minister and following the removal of his credentials of ordination. Series contains two subseries, Engagements and RRNGLE (Raleigh Religious Network for Gay and Lesbian Equality). Series comprises Creech's original files which tend to be both subject files as well his personal files about the organizations and projects he worked with. The series covers his advocacy for LGBT rights, primarily marriage equality and making faith communities welcoming to LGBT-identified congregants. Files contain his work to found and guide several organizations to support LGBT people of faith, namely Faith in America and Soulforce. Also included is correspondence with other religious LGBT activists, articles and clippings, and printed material. Series contains files related to his work against the death penalty. Creech had pastoral relationships with death row inmates in North Carolina.
  - Engagements, 3
    Engagements subseries contains notes, ephemera, printed material, and correspondence from Creech's speaking engagements at churches, conferences, colleges, and universities around the country from 1996 to 2014.
    - Notes for Talks, 1998-2014 (Box 7)
    - Paul Green Award, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
    - Riverside Church, 1998 June (Box 7)
    - Metropolitan Community Church San Francisco, 1998 September (Box 7)
    - Monday Chib (?), NY and Parkslope UMC, 1998 October (Box 7)
    - California Methodist Federation for Social Action Retreat, San Rafael, 1998 November (Box 7)
    - Allegheny College, 1998 (Box 7)
    - West Hollywood Presbyterian Church, 1998 November (Box 7)
    - University Temple UMC, 1999 January 17 (Box 7)
    - Hickory, NC, 1999 (Box 7)
    - Celebration in Spirit San Jose, 1999 June 12 (Box 7)
    - Los Gatos UMC, 1999 June 03 (Box 7)
    - Princeton University, 1999 April 25 (Box 7)
    - PFLAG Conference, Chicago, 1999 June 05 (Box 7)
    - MFSA Banquet, Baltimore - Washington Conference. Washington DC, 1999 June 10 (Box 7)
    - PFLAG Conference, Chattanooga, 1999 September 18 (Box 7)
    - Lynchburg, VA, 1999 October 22-24 (Box 7)
    - Penn State U, 1999 October 2-5 (Box 7)
    - Sharing our Rainbow Light IV, Washington DC, 1999 November 11 (Box 7)
    - Harrisburg, 2000 January 15-18 (Box 7)
    - Morningside College, 2000 February (Box 7)
    - N. Raleigh UC, 2000 March 5 (Box 7)
    - Greensboro College, 2000 March 15 (Box 7)
    - St. Jude's MCC Wilmington, NC., 2000 April 23 (Box 7)
    - Christ Covenant, 1999 February (Box 7)
    - Common Pain, Common Hope - Chicago, Marelizo, 1999 March 19 (Box 7)
    - Phoenix/Tucson, 1999 March 20-22 (Box 7)
    - Religious Roundtable Colorado Springs, 1999 April 23-25 (Box 7)
    - Peace w/ Justice Week Henderson, Kentucky, 1999 October 15-17 (Box 7)
    - All God's Children Conference Roanoke, VA, 1999 November 5 (Box 7)
    - Omaha, March 6-7, 2000 (Box 7)
    - National PFLAG Conference, April 28-29, 2000 (Box 7)
    - Chicago Temple UMC, 2000 May 21 (Box 7)
    - Omaha, NE, 2000 September 8-10 (Box 7)
    - Jesus MCC, Indianapolis, 2000 September 16-18 (Box 7)
    - Metropolitan Community Church Los Angeles Fundraiser, 2000 October 7 (Box 7)
    - Monadock Summer Lyceum, 2000 July 30 (Box 7)
    - GLAD MCC Conference, 1999 November 19-21 (Box 7)
    - Texas, 2000 February 4-8 (Box 7)
    - Opening Doors, Yale U, 2000 February 25 (Box 7)
    - Soulforce in Denver, 2000 July 4 (Box 7)
    - Community Church of CH, 2000 June 11 (Box 7)
    - Millennium March and PFLAG, 2000 April 28-30 (Box 7)
    - Cathedral of Hope Dallas/TX, 1999 April 10-11 (Box 7)
    - King of Peace Metropolitan Community Church St. Petersburg, Florida, 2000 July 16 (Box 7)
    - WOW Conference, Delzab, IL, 2000 July 3-6 (Box 7)
    - Solidarity Sunday, 2000 October 8 (Box 7)
    - Wesley UMC, Fresno, CA, 2000 October 15 (Box 7)
    - Third Annual Prayer Gathering for Truth, Courage, and Justice, 2000 September 16-18 (Box 7)
    - Santa Cruz, CA, 2001 February 3-5 (Box 7)
    - PRP Conference, Washington DC, 2001 April 4-6 (Box 7)
    - PFLAG, Greenville, SC, 2001 November 30 (Box 7)
    - Pacific School of Religion, April 19-20, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Presbyterian General Convention, 2001 June 9 (Box 7)
    - Evangelical Lutheran Church of America Church-wide Assembly, Indianapolis, IN, 2001 August 10-14 (Box 7)
    - Austin, TX, 2002 (Box 7)
    - Dallas HRC, 2004 September 17-19 (Box 7)
    - FUMC, Boulder, CO, 2005 March 3-6 (Box 7)
    - Liberty Education Forum National Symposium, 2005 April 1 (Box 7)
    - Soulforce NYC, 2005 April 21-24; 1 folder (Box 7)
    - eQuality giving meeting Dallas, TX, 2009 May 15-17 (Box 7)
    - Frank Porter Graham Award ACLU-NC, undated (Box 7)
    - FUMC, Omaha, NE, 2005 September 15-18 (Box 7)
    - Institute of Politics, Cambridge, MA, 2004 October 20 (Box 7)
    - OutFront Conference and Country Club Congregational UCC Kansas City, MO, 2007 February 10-11 (Box 7)
    - Church of the Good Shepherd United Church of Christ Albuquerque, NM, 2006 February 11-13; 1 folder (Box 7)